Hugo Leichtentritt Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Hugo Leichtentritt Papers 1888-1972 (bulk 1890-1933)
ML31.L45
Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951
1,600 items 23 containers 10.0 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Hugo Leichtentritt was a German musicologist, music critic, and composer. The collection contains his original music manuscripts, correspondence, clippings, programs, scrapbooks, articles and drafts of his writings on music history, criticism, and theory.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951--Archives.; Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951--Correspondence.; Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951--Manuscripts.; Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951.; Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951.; Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951. Music of the Western nations.; Leichtentritt, Hugo, 1874-1951. Selections.
Subjects
Composers.; Music critics.; Music--History and criticism.; Music--Manuscripts.; Music--Performance--History.; Musical criticism.; Musicologists.
Form/Genre
Articles.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (Documents); Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Nicolas Slonimsky, circa 1952.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division holds the
Nicolas Slonimsky Collection
(ML31.S6) and
Serge Koussevitzky Archive
(ML31.K66), both of which contain correspondence from Leichtentritt.
Access and Restrictions
The Hugo Leichtentritt Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1874, Jan. 1 Born in the province of Posen, Prussia
1891-1894 Attended Harvard University
1894-1895 Continued musical studies in Paris
1895-1898 Attended the Hochschule für Musik in Berlin
1898-1901 Ph.D., in Philosophy, Berlin University; dissertation entitled Reinhard Keiser in seinen Opern
1901-1924 Taught at the Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatory in Berlin
1901-1933 Gave private composition lessons and wrote music criticism for various German and American publications
1933 Left Germany to lecture at Harvard University
1940 Retired from Harvard University
1940-1944 Lecturer, Radcliffe College, Cambridge, Mass. and New York University
1951, Nov. 13 Died, Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The Hugo Leichtentritt Papers consist of music manuscripts, correspondence, clippings, programs, scrapbooks, and writings on music history, criticism, and theory. The collection spans the period 1888 to 1972, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1890 to the 1933.
Leichtentritt's personal compositions include songs, and works for solo piano, organ, small instrumental combinations, and orchestra. These are chiefly represented by manuscript scores, parts, and sketches. Leichtentritt's dramatic works are often regarded as his most significant original compositions: Esther (1923-1926), Cantata, op. 27: Ich bin eine Blume zu Saron (1930), and his comedic opera, Der Sizilianer (1915-1918). A handwritten thematic index, located in box 21, provides details about the history of many of his compositions. Leichtentritt frequently reconstructed or arranged the compositions of other composers to illustrate concepts for teaching. These are respresented in the subseries of "Music by Other Composers" alongside scores and parts by various composers, including Bach, Haydn, Handel, and Monteverdi. Lichtentritt's settings of texts by the German poets Richard Dehmel and Friedrich Hölderlin are extensively represented.
The collection also contains seven scrapbooks that date from 1888 to 1933. These span Leichtentritt's early career, from his years as an undergraduate at Harvard University, through his employment at the Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatory in Berlin, to his later hiring by Harvard in 1933. The albums chiefly contain articles, clippings, correspondence, programs, and promotional material in German and English about various musical performances and composers.
Leichtentritt's writings consist of manuscript and typescript drafts of articles, essays, critical commentary, and analyses. Most notable are the materials for his book Music of the Western Nations, which was published posthumously by Nicolas Slonimsky in 1956. Although the final version contained twelve chapters, there are fourteen present in his draft, including a foreword, introduction, and index. Equally intriguing is Leichtentritt's unfinished autobiography that chronicles his military life in Germany during World War I, his travels throughout Europe, and his seven-year tenure as a lecturer at Harvard University. The collection also contains a draft of his 1901 dissertation, Reinhard Keiser in seinen Opern, which he submitted for his Doctorate of Philosophy degree from Berlin University. Other writings include a work on the history of motet music and analyses of compositions by Chopin, Copland, Handel, and Monteverdi.
Organization of the Hugo Leichtentritt Papers
The Hugo Leichtentritt Papers are organized in four series:
Music, 1893-1972
Scrapbooks, 1888-1933
Writings, 1892-1956
Miscellany, 1889-1931
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012562125
Container List
- Music, 1893-1972 (Box 1-14, 22-23)
  - Music by Leichtentritt
    Manuscript and published scores, parts, and sketches. Researchers should consult Leichtentritt's thematic index for more detailed compositional histories of select works.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - 4 stimmen Fuge (piano), 1896, Score (Box-folder 1/1)
    - The 7 penitential psalms (voices, chorus, orchestra), undated, Score (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Allegro maestoso (piano), 1893, Score (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Andante, op. 1 (piano), 1890, Sketch (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Aus dem 106 Psalmen für 3 Stimmen mit Klavier, 1892, Title page (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Canon in der Oktave (piano), 1896-1897, Scores (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Cantata for contralto solo and orchestra, or piano, on selected verses from the canticle of Solomon, op. 27: Ich bin eine Blume zu Saron, 1930, Score (Box-folder 1/7-11, 22/1)
    - Ca'tchua (orchestra), 1908, Score fragment (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Chinesisch-deutsche Jahres-und Tageszeiten von Goethe (no. 1-8), op.4: ein Liederzyklus (voice, orchestra), 1912, Scores (Box-folder 2/1-2)
    - Concert for cello and orchestra, op. 24, 1927, Scores and sketches (Box-folder 2/3-6)
    - Concerto for violin and orchestra, op. 14, undated, Scores and violin solo parts (Box-folder 2/7-8, 3/1-2)
    - Cyprian de rose (voices), 1892, Score (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Danket dem Herrn, denn er ist freundlich (double chorus), 1899, Score (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Dirge of Saul: for baritone solo, women's chorus, and instruments, circa 1944?, Score and sketches (Box-folder 3/5-6)
    - Doppelter contrapunkt, 1897, Exercises (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Dreistrimmiger [?] canon, undated, Sketch (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Esther: dramatische Legende nach der Bibel (voices, violin, organ), 1914, Score; Incomplete (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Esther: dramatische Legende nach der Bibel (voices, chorus, orchestra), 1923-1926 and undated, Scores and sketches (Box-folder 3/10-11, 4/1-2, 22/2-4, 23/1-2)
    - Etude (piano), undated, Score (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Etude (piano), undated, Score and sketches (Box-folder 23/3)
    - Etude (piano), 1932, Score (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Etude no. 1 (piano), undated, Score (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Etude no. 3 (piano), undated, Score (Box-folder 4/6)
    - From the 130th psalm (voices, chorus, orchestra), 1897, Scores (Box-folder 4/7-8)
    - Des Frühlings Ankunft (voice, piano), 1910, Score (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Hero und Leander: op. 30, undated, Parts (Box-folder 4/10-12, 5/1-3)
    - Ich sehe dich in Tausend bildern: op. 2, no. 7 (voice, piano), 1910, Printed score (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Introitus solemnis: for organ, op. 33, 1933 see also Prelude for organ, Printed score (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Jewish marching song (voice or chorus, piano), undated, Score (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Kol nidreh: for mixed chorus and organ, undated, Score; Laid in: solo voice arrangements by Louis Lewandowski and an unidentified composer, used as source material by Leichtentritt (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Kontrapunkt, 1895-1897, Exercises (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Lieder und Gesänge, op. 2 and 3 (voice, piano), 1909-1910 and undated, Scores (Box-folder 5/9-10)
    - Miscellaneous compositions, undated, Sketches and fragments (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Piano concerto (piano, orchestra), 1929, Score; Incomplete or unfinished (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Piano quintet, op. 14, 1914, Score (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Prelude for organ, 1930 see also Introitus solemnis, Score (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Psalm 2 (voices, orchestra), 1897, Score; Unfinished (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Scherzo and trio (piano), 1895, Score (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Schwimm hin, Ringelein: aus Des Knaben Wunderhorn (voice, piano), 1909-1910, Score (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Der Sizilianer (voices, orchestra), 1915-1918, Scores, vocal part for "Isadore", and librettos (Box-folder 6/6-11, 23/4)
    - Sonata for cello and piano, 1929, Scores and corrections (Box-folder 7/1-3)
    - Sonata for piano, 1898, Score and sketches; Includes revised Finale (Box-folder 7/4-5)
    - Sonata for piano, op. 23, 1926, Scores (Box-folder 7/6-9, 23/5)
    - Sonata for viola and piano, op. 13, 1913, Scores and viola part (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Sonata for violin and piano, op. 17, 1919, Scores, violin part, and sketches (Box-folder 7/11-13)
    - Song for the twentieth reunion of the class of 1894, Harvard College (voice, piano), 1914, Score (Box-folder 7/14)
    - String quartet, 1894, Score (Box-folder 7/15)
    - String quartet, 1897, Score (Box-folder 7/16)
    - String quartet, op. 1, 1913, Printed score; Annotations (Box-folder 7/17)
    - String quartet, op. 7, undated, Score (Box-folder 7/18)
    - String quartet no. 2, op. 20, undated, Parts (Box-folder 8/1)
    - String quartet no. 3, undated, Scores and parts (Box-folder 8/2-3)
    - Suite for cello solo, undated, Title page (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Suite for harpsichord, op. 31, 1932, Score (Box-folder 8/5)
    - A summer day: tone poem for women's chorus and chamber orchestra, op. 11, undated, Scores and double bass part (Box-folder 8/6-8)
    - Symphonic suite (orchestra), undated, Scores and sketches; Unfinished (Box-folder 8/9-12)
    - Tenebrae factae sunt (voices), undated, Score (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Theme (piano), 1893, Score (Box-folder 8/14)
    - Theme and variations for piano, op. 26, 1930, Scores and sketches (Box-folder 9/1-3)
    - Theme and variations for string quartet, undated, Score and parts; Incomplete (Box-folder 9/4-5)
    - Toccata and fugue for piano, op. 29, 1931, Score and sketches (Box-folder 9/6-7)
    - Variations on a Siamese melody: for orchestra, 1931, Score (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Unidentified, undated, Sketches (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Music by Other Composers
    Manuscript and printed scores and parts in the hands of Leichtentritt and other composers. Includes manuscript copies and arrangements by Leichtentritt used for student instruction.
    Arranged alphabetically by composer and title of work therein.
    - A-Ca (Box-folder 9/10-9/20)
    - Ch-Deh (Box-folder 10/1-10/41)
    - Del-Ha (Box-folder 11/1-11/46)
    - He-Ho (Box-folder 12/1-12/27)
    - Ho-Mu (Box-folder 13/1-13/30)
    - No-V (Box-folder 14/1-14/42, 23/6)
- Scrapbooks, 1888-1933 (Box 15-16)
  Unbound volumes of articles, clippings, correspondence, and programs.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1880s-1920s and undated (Box-folder 15/1-15/4)
  - 1918-1933 and undated (Box-folder 16/1-16/3)
- Writings, 1892-1956 (Box 17-21)
  Manuscript and typescript drafts of book chapters, articles, essays, and other writings on music history. Includes Leichtentritt's unfinished autobiography and his journal from 1893.
  - "Aaron Copland: Third symphony," 1946 (Box-folder 18/1)
  - "The American scene of music," undated (Box-folder 18/2)
  - Analyse der Chopin'schen Klavierwerke, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 18/3-4)
  - Autobiography, undated (Box-folder 18/5-8)
  - "Claudio Monteverdi as Madrigalkomponist," undated (Box-folder 19/1)
  - "Essais et critiques," 1893-1894 (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Geschichte der Motette, 1908 (Box-folder 19/3-5)
  - Handel, 1924 (Box-folder 17/1-3)
  - "History of ancient art," 1892-1893 (Box-folder 19/6)
  - "Jean Sibelius: Fifth symphony," undated (Box-folder 19/7)
  - "Julius Caesar," undated (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Music, history, and ideas, undated, Introduction only (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Music of the Western nations, 1956 (Box-folder 20/4-8)
  - "Nationalism and internationalism in music," undated, Chapter 10 from an unidentified work (Box-folder 20/9)
  - "Die Oper," undated (Box-folder 21/1)
  - "Protestant music and the Reformation," 1934 (Box-folder 21/2)
  - "The reform of Trent," undated (Box-folder 21/3)
  - "Reinhard Keiser in seinen Opern," 1901 (Box-folder 21/4)
  - "Schubert," undated (Box-folder 21/5)
  - Tagebuch, 1893 (Box-folder 21/6)
- Miscellany, 1889-1931 (Box 21)
  One article, two programs, and a thematic index of Leichtentritt's musical compositions.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - "Bericht über die fünfte Hauptversammlung," 1920, Article that mentions Leichtentritt (Box-folder 21/7)
  - Programs, 1889, 1931 (Box-folder 21/8)
  - Thematic index, undated, Index cards with bibliographic information for Leichtentritt's compositions (Box-folder 21/9)